A Guide to the Ford Foundation records, Economic Opportunity and Assets Program, Metropolitan Opportunity Unit, Office Files of Elizabeth McKeon FA1235
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation records, Economic Opportunity and Assets Program, Metropolitan Opportunity Unit, Office Files of Elizabeth McKeon
1994-2012
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation
McKeon, Elizabeth
FA1235
1.9 Cubic Feet 5 letter size boxes
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research with select materials restricted as noted.
Scope and Contents
Collection contains the office files Elizabeth, "Liz", McKeon created when she worked at the Ford Foundation as the Foundation's Representative for Russia and then as Director for the Special Initiative on Urban Poverty in Developing Countries. When McKeon was Representative for Russia, she was based in the Foundation's Moscow Field Office until its closure. She then moved to direct the Special Initiative on Urban Poverty in Developing Countries within the Metropolitan Opportunity unit (MOU) of the Economic Opportunity and Assets Program (EOA).
The collection is comprised of three series containing subject files, grant files, and meetings and trips files. Subject and grant files document the work McKeon performed when she was responsible for the Ford Foundation's programming for Russia and Eastern Europe and worked in the Moscow Office. The grant files show how McKeon continued managing the close out of the Russia grants after the Moscow Office closed and she moved to the EOA. Meetings and trips files span across McKeon's tenures as Russia Representative and Director for the Special Initiative on Urban Poverty in Developing Countries.
Files in the collection pertaining to the Ford Foundation's programming for Russia and Eastern Europe document the Foundation's interests in arts and culture, media and journalism, human rights, medicine, legal education, and people with disabilities. These materials also document the history of the Moscow Field Office from the Foundation's plans to open the office in the mid-1990s to the Foundation's decision to close the office in 2009. Records discuss some of the difficulties the Foundation and other foreign NGOs had working in Russia towards the end of the Moscow Office's history.
Files created by McKeon when she served as Director for the Special Initiative on Urban Poverty in Developing Countries document that initiative's focus on combatting urban poverty in the Global South through socially inclusive urban planning and economic development.
Common material formats found within the collection include memos, correspondence, notes, drafts, reports, articles, grant reports, grant modifications, grant actions records, meeting materials, travel itineraries and other travel related documents, and publications.
Arrangement
Collection is comprised of three series.
Original order was maintained as much as possible.
The collection arrangement is as follows:
Series 1. Moscow Field Office subject files, 1994-2011
Series 2. Moscow Field Office grant files, 2001-2012
Series 3. Meetings and trips files, 2005-2011
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Ford Foundation archive was deposited at the RAC in 2011. Ford Foundation records, correspondence, reports, program files, and officers' papers were transferred to and accessioned by the RAC beginning in 2011. Accessions continue as necessary.
This material was transferred to the RAC in two accessions in 2020 and 2022 and was ingested by the RAC as Accessions 2020:031 and 2022:028.
Ford Foundation; Russia; Europe, Eastern; City planning; Community development, Urban; Economic development; Human rights
- Moscow Field Office subject files, 1994-2011; 1; .57 Cubic Feet 1.5 letter size boxes
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains subject files related to the Russia and Eastern Europe programming of the Ford Foundation's Moscow Field Office. These files were created and maintained by Elizabeth McKeon, the Foundation's last Representative for Russia before the Foundation closed the Moscow Office. The series also includes files created by McKeon's predecessors as Representative for Russia, Mary McAuley and Steven Solnick.
  The files give insight into the Ford Foundation's activities and history in Russia and Eastern Europe as well as the history of broader international philanthropy in the region. Earlier records in the series document the Foundation's planning and opening of its Moscow Office and give an overview of the office's grants. Later materials in the series show how changes in Russia impacted the Ford Foundation and other international NGOs working in the country such as the Russian government's adoption of Decree 485 which took away the tax-exempt status of grants issued by foreign NGOs like the Ford Foundation.
  The files document the Ford Foundation's program interests in economic development, arts and culture, and human rights in Russia. There is also a draft report McKeon created when she worked at the United States Agency for International Development (USAID) that she shared with the Ford Foundation before she started working there.
  - Affinity Group - Russia, 2010 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Rights under law, 2009-2011 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - The Paul Klebnikov Fund, 2009 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Workforce development report draft – Elizabeth McKeon, United States Agency for International Development (USAID), 2004 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Workforce development – Rick McGahey Program Officer Memo, 2008 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Moscow, Russia Field Office Exit Memos, 1998-2008 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Moscow, Russia Field Office administration and 2006 Kremlin meeting, 1997-2006 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Development of Moscow, Russia Field Office and Moscow Office assets programming, 1994-2001 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Security situation in Moscow, Russia – Memo, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Visas accreditation, 2008-2009 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Russian Government Decree 485 – Foreign NGO tax status, 2007-2009 (Box 1, Folder 11-12)
  - Russian Government Decree 485 – Foreign NGO tax status, 2008-2010 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Moscow, Russia Field Office program strategy, 1996-2000 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Moscow, Russia Field Office grants – General reports on projects, 1996-1998 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Former Ford Foundation Representative for Russia Mary McAuley memos – Ford Foundation staff visits to Russia, 2000-2001 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - The John Smith Memorial Trust, 2008-2009 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Pakistan Flood Disaster Relief Trust, 2010 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Mark Willis, Visiting Scholar biography, 2008 August 6 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - John D. and Catherine T. MacArthur Foundation, 2006-2007 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - United States Agency for International Development (USAID)/Russia Strategy Amendment, 2002 (Box 2, Folder 21)
- Moscow Field Office grant files, 2001-2012; 2; .95 Cubic Feet 2.5 letter size boxes
  This series contains grant files from the portfolio Elizabeth McKeon maintained when she worked as the Ford Foundation Representative for Russia and Eastern Europe in the Moscow Field Office. Most of the files contain narrative and financial grant reports. Correspondence, grant modifications, and grant action records can also be found in several files.
  Grantees documented in the series worked in various areas such as human rights, arts and culture, media and journalism, legal education, medicine, and supporting people with disabilities. The dates on the reports show how McKeon managed the close-out of these grants after the Moscow Office closed.
  - ANCO Media, Grant No. 1000-1553-7, 2009-2010 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - ANNA, Grant No. 1050-0914-2, 2009-2011 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - ANO Creative Association, Grant No. 1075-0436-2, 2010 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Baikal Environmental Wave, Grant No. 1095-0186, 2008-2009 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Bard College/Smolny College, Grant No. 1065-1073, 2008-2010 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Center for Curative Pedagogics (CCP), Grant No. 1080-1090, 2010 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Center for Strategic and International Studies (CSIS), Grant No. 1070-0109, 2009-2010 (Box 2, Folder 28-29)
  - Charities Aid Foundation (CAF), Grant No. 1050-0918-1 - People living with HIV/AIDS, 2010-2011 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Good Neighbor, Grant No. 1095-0235, 2010 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Citizens' Watch (CW), Grant No. 1085-0640, 2008-2010 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Civic Analysis and Independent Research Center (GRANI), Grant No. 1080-1058, 2010-2012 (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - European University of St. Petersburg (EUSP), Grant No. 1080-1405, 2009-2011 (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Eyge Environmental Education Center, Grant No. 1095-0158, 2010-2011 (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - Foundation for Independent Radio Broadcasting, Grant No. 1095-0316, 2009 (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - Foundation for Interregional Projects, Grant No. 1080-1052, 2010 (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - Friends of Siberian Forests, Grant No. 1095-0184, 2010 (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - Human Rights Network Group, Grant No. 1070-0268, 2009 (Box 3, Folder 39)
  - Helsinki Foundation for Human Rights, Grant No. 1055-0835, 2010 (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - Informatics for Democracy (INDEM), Grant No. 1050-0624-4, 2010 (Box 3, Folder 41)
  - Interregional Human Rights Network Group, Grant No. 1070-0268-1, 2010 (Box 3, Folder 42)
  - Kaliningrad Branch of the National Centre for Contemporary Arts (NCAA), Grant No. 1080-0301, 2009 (Box 3, Folder 43)
  - Khabarovsk Krai Charitable Public Interests, Grant No. 1095-0160-0, 2010 (Box 3, Folder 44)
  - Kuntskamera (Peter the Great Museum of Anthropology and Ethnology at the Russian Academy of Sciences), Grant No. 1085-1035-0, 2009 (Box 3, Folder 45)
  - KOMART club, Grant No. 1080-0552, 2010 (Box 3, Folder 46)
  - Clinical Legal Education Foundation (CLEF), Grant No. 1050-0620-1, 2009-2010 (Box 3, Folder 47)
  - Law and Justice Foundation, Grant No. 1080-0338-1, 2009-2010 (Box 3, Folder 48)
  - Levada Analytical Center, Grant No. 1090-0688, 2009-2011 (Box 3, Folder 49)
  - Partners in Health (PIH), Grant No. 1075-0582-2, 2009 (Box 3, Folder 50)
  - The Forest Village, Grant No. 1085-0581-0, 2010 (Box 3, Folder 51)
  - Moscow Association for Disabled Children and their Families, Grant No. 1085-0894-1, 2010 (Box 3, Folder 52)
  - National Centre for Contemporary Arts (NCCA), Grant No. 1095-0704, 2009 (Box 3, Folder 53)
  - Nizhniy Novgorod Branch, National Centre for Contemporary Arts (NCAA) Grant No. 1010-0412-4, 2010 (Box 3, Folder 54)
  - Nonprofit Partin Grantmakers Donor Forum, Grant No. 1095-1123, 2010 (Box 3, Folder 55)
  - TsEKh (NP Dance Theatres Network), Grant No. 1080-1281, 2010 (Box 3, Folder 56)
  - Objective Reality Foundation, Grant No. 1095-0419-0, 2010 (Box 3, Folder 57)
  - Objective Reality Foundation, Grant No. 1095-0419-0, 2010 (Box 3, Folder 58)
  - Pavlov State Medical University, Grant No. 1080-0691, 2010 (Box 3, Folder 59)
  - Pavlov State Medical University, Grant No. 1080-0691, 2010-2011 (Box 3, Folder 60)
  - Partners in Health (PIH), Grant No. 1075-0582-2, 2010 (Box 3, Folder 61)
  - Perm Civic Chamber, Grant No. 1085-1143-0, 2010 (Box 3, Folder 62)
  - PILI, Grant No. 1090-0582, 2010 (Box 3, Folder 63)
  - St. Petersburg PRO ARTE Foundation for Culture and the Arts, Grant No. 1020-0468, 2009-2012 (Box 3, Folder 64)
  - Robin Hessman, Red Square Productions, Grant No. 1095-0724-0, 2009-2011 (Box 3, Folder 65)
  - RIC Memorial, Grant No. 1095-0432, 2010-2011 (Box 3, Folder 66)
  - Russian Lawyers Committee in Defense of Human Rights (RLCHR), Grant No. 1070-0749, 2010-2011 (Box 3, Folder 67)
  - Russian State Archives of Literature and Art, Grant No. 1060-0943, 2010 (Box 3, Folder 68)
  - Central State Archive of Film and Photographic Documents, St. Petersburg, Russia, Grant No. 1080-0842, 2009-2011 (Box 3, Folder 69)
  - The Moscow Guild for Theater and Screen Actors, Grant No. 1000-0292-7, 2009 (Box 3, Folder 70)
  - TsEKh (NP Dance Theatres Network), Grant No. 1060-0243-2, 2009 (Box 3, Folder 71)
  - TsEKh (NP Dance Theatres Network), Grant No. 1080-1281, 2009 (Box 3, Folder 72)
  - United Nations Educational, Scientific, and Cultural Organization (UNESCO), Grant No. 1085-0913, 2010 (Box 3, Folder 73)
  - Wildlife Conservation Society (WCS), Grant No. 1095-0159, 2010 (Box 3, Folder 74)
  - Center of Contemporary Architecture, Grant No. 1020-1183-3, 2010 (Box 3, Folder 75)
  - New Economic School (NES), Grant No. 1080-0689-1, 2010 (Box 5, Folder 101)
  - MEMO RU, Grant No. 1060-1103-1, 2009-2010 (Box 5, Folder 102)
  - Memorial International Society, 2001-2005 (Box 5, Folder 103)
  - Memorial International Society, Grant No. 1070-0523-1, 2010 (Box 5, Folder 104)
- Meetings and trips files, 2005-2011; 3; .38 Cubic Feet 1 letter size box
  This series contains meetings and trips files Elizabeth McKeon created and maintained when she worked as the Ford Foundation's Representative for Russia and Eastern Europe and Director for the Special Initiative on Urban Poverty in Developing Countries. The files contain itineraries and other travel documents that provide evidence of the travel McKeon made for these trips. There are also materials such as correspondence, agendas, notes, and reports present in the series which document the substance of the meetings and visits McKeon had. Users should note that several files in the series contain just travel documents.
  For the most part, the files are arranged chronologically. The first few files document trips McKeon made as Representative for Russia and include materials related to grantee visits. Some files created from when McKeon later served as Director for the Special Initiative on Urban Poverty in Developing Countries show how she finished off activities related to the Foundation's Russia and Eastern Europe program after the Moscow Office closed.
  Trip files related to McKeon's work for the Special Initiative on Urban Poverty in Developing Countries within the Economic Opportunity and Assets Program (EOA) Metropolitan Opportunity Unit (MOU) document McKeon participating in meetings and site visits related to urban planning and development throughout various countries. One file contains materials from the first convening of the Ford Foundation's Learning Group on Urban Poverty in Developing Countries in Jakarta, Indonesia.
  - Beijing, China December 2008 trip - Ford Foundation Asia and Russia Representative Rap (Box 4, Folder 76)
  - St. Petersburg, Russia October 2008 trip - Ford Foundation International Fellowships Program (IFP) (Box 4, Folder 77)
  - St. Petersburg, Russia September 2008 trip - Grantee visits (Box 4, Folder 78)
  - Mexico City, Mexico Office November 2008 visit (Box 4, Folder 79)
  - Washington, D.C. January 2010 trip (Box 4, Folder 80)
  - Park City, Utah trip, January 2010 - Sundance Film Festival, 2009-2010 (Box 4, Folder 81)
  - Cape Town and Johannesburg, South Africa and London, England February 2010 trips, 2008-2010 (Box 4, Folder 82)
  - Moscow, Russia February 2010 trip (Box 4, Folder 83)
  - Rio de Janeiro, Brazil 2010 trip - World Urban Forum (Box 4, Folder 84)
  - Boston, Massachusetts April 2010 trip (Box 4, Folder 85)
  - Cuzco, Peru April 2010 trip - Ford Foundation Trustees (Box 4, Folder 86)
  - Belfast, Northern Ireland June 2010 trip - Absent historical memory (Box 4, Folder 87)
  - Washington D.C. June 2010 trips (Box 4, Folder 88)
  - Cambridge, Massachusetts July 2010 trip - Massachusetts Institute of Technology (MIT) (Box 4, Folder 89)
  - San Diego, California and Tijuana, Mexico August 2010 trip (Box 4, Folder 90)
  - Manchester, England September 2010 trip (Box 4, Folder 91)
  - Johannesburg, South Africa September 2010 trip (Box 4, Folder 92)
  - Namibia, South Africa, and Kenya November 2010 trip, 2005-2010 (Box 4, Folder 93)
  - Colombia 2010 trip (Box 4, Folder 94)
  - Tijuana, Mexico January 2011 trip, 2010-2011 (Box 4, Folder 95)
  - India 2011 trip (Box 4, Folder 96)
  - Cambridge, Massachusetts May 2011 trip - Building Assets for the Urban Poor by Design (Box 4, Folder 97)
  - Sheffield and London, England June 2011 trip - Sheffield Doc/Fest, 2010-2011 (Box 4, Folder 98)
  - Moscow, Russia and Berlin, Germany September 2011 trip (Box 4, Folder 99)
  - Jakarta, Indonesia 2010 trip - Learning Group on Urban Poverty in Developing Countries convening (Box 4, Folder 100)